<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good news from Kent Being a true relation of an hundred and twenty peeces of ordnance taken neere Gravesend, and of five cart loads taken from Cobham Hall, August 20. And a discovery of ammunition for five hundred men taken from the Archbishop of Canterburies house at Lambeth on friday night last. Also a description of the battell between the Hollanders and nine ships of Dunkirk going to aid the rebels in Ireland, and how after three houres fight they were surprized by the Hollanders. H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1060A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825786</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825786</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30174</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41409)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30174)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1793:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good news from Kent Being a true relation of an hundred and twenty peeces of ordnance taken neere Gravesend, and of five cart loads taken from Cobham Hall, August 20. And a discovery of ammunition for five hundred men taken from the Archbishop of Canterburies house at Lambeth on friday night last. Also a description of the battell between the Hollanders and nine ships of Dunkirk going to aid the rebels in Ireland, and how after three houres fight they were surprized by the Hollanders. H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Io. Iohnson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August 22. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kent (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30174:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30174:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOOD NEWES FROM KENT.</p>
            <p>Being a true Relation of an hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty peeces of Ordnance taken neere <hi>Graveſend,</hi> and of five cart loads taken from <hi>Cobham Hall,</hi> Auguſt 20.</p>
            <p>AND A diſcovery of ammunition for five hundred men taken from the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburies</hi> houſe at <hi>Lambeth</hi> on friday night laſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo a deſcription of the battell between the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and nine ſhips of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> going to aid the Rebels in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and how after three houres ſight they were ſurprized by the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Io. Iohnſon. Auguſt</hi> 22. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30174:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30174:2"/>
            <head>JOYFULL NEWES FROM COBHAM-HALL IN KENT. Being a true Relation of ſuch armes as were taken from thence Auguſt 20. ALSO A Diſcovery of ſuch Ammunition as was taken from the Arthbiſhop of Canterbury <hi>Aug. 19.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch hath beene the providence and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancie of this our Parliament, having been ſo proſperouſly ſeconded with the bleſsing of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their endeavours that they have been ſucceſſefull even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond hope, in detecting and defeating the plots of the malignant party, how cunningly ſoever by them contrived. Vpon the nineteenth of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30174:3"/>this moneth the Parliament received informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of about an hundred and twenty pieces of Ordnance that lay neere the water ſide foure miles from Graveſend, which cauſeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants to watch them every night, fearing leſt thoſe which are ill-affected to the King and Parliament ſhould poſſeſſe themſelves of them or ſteale ſome of them away, many of them being ſo ſmall, that they might be carried away by two or three men, which might prove very preiudiciall to the peace of that countrey: whereupon the Parliament have taken order for the ſecuring and ſafe keeping of them.</p>
            <p>No ſooner is one pernicious deſigne diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, but another ſupplies the roome of it: for information being given to the Parliament-Houſe, that great ſtore of armes and ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was provided by that arch-ploiter of theſe evils, the Arch-biſhop of Canterbury, and laid up in his houſe at Lambeth, the ſame evening, being friday, about two hundred Foot, and a troop of Horſe were ſent to ſearch his houſe, wherein they found armes for foure or five hundred men, all which they tooke away from his houſe at Lambeth, and laid them in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty having little need of ſuch ammunition for his defence, being better provided in the Tower ſince hee kept Court there. Vpon the ſame evening a troupe of Horſe were ſent into Kent to ſearch ſome Recuſants houſes which were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30174:3"/>ſuſpected to have great ſtore of armes and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and coming to make ſearch at Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham-Hall, they were denied entrance, and very much reſiſted, though little hurt was done, as is credibly reported, notwithſtanding the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of ſo many being hurt and ſlaine: after much oppoſition they entred the houſe, and found there five cart loads of ammunition, which they have taken away, intending to bring it up to London. Vpon this day alſo Sir John Meldrom that was ſent to Hull, according to the deſire of Sir John Hotham, by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for to aid and aſsiſt him in the defence of that towne, came to the Parliament Houſe, and acquainted them with the true ſtate of of things there, and that Sir John Hotham hath ſo cleared the coaſts about him by ſea and land, that the Cavaliers dare not ſo much as to come neer the towne. As for the maior part of Yorkſhire, they are ſo well affected to the Parliament, that when as His Maieſty had commanded all his loving ſubiects to repaire unto him that would aid and aſsiſt him, the chiefeſt of the Gentry of that countrey refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to obey the ſaid command, and are reſolved to aſsiſt the Parliament againſt all that ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, profering their own perſons to both Houſes to maintaine the ſaid Cauſe: and for that end have deſired the Parliament to ſend ſuch forces as might ſecure them in ſo doing.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:30174:4"/>
            <p>As the faces of all <hi>Britaine</hi> ſhew their hearts and inclinations, ſo if their hearts were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, and as perſpicuous as their faces, they would appeare fearfull of the future, were not the Repreſentative Body of the State carefull to cure the preſent malady, by qualifying and tempering the diſtempered humours, and ſave the much indangered body, by cutting off ſome rotten and putrified members which infect, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and invade the republique: and herein conſiſts a great part of the happineſſe of this Kingdome, which (next under the Searcher of hearts) is derived unto us by the pious care and induſtry of the Parliament, in that they have been ſo ſucceſſefull in diſcovering and ſearching out of the plots &amp; machinations of the adverſe party, and ſo indulgent and friendly to all ſuch as are well-affected to the peace and welfare of this Kingdome. Nor is there amity and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip circumſcribed and terminated within this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> but is further ſhewed in the unity and correſpondence betwixt us and our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> though ſo many ill-affected ſpirits have endeavoured a disiunction. A further degree of our happines in this Iſland is to be ſeen in the mutuall concord betwixt us and the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> whoſe confederacie with this Nation hath been happy, and all their deſignes ſeconded with ſucceſſe ſince their firſt union. They have lately declared their fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30174:4"/>and good affection to the Parliament in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine letters preſented to the Houſe, wherein is intimated and declared to them their true, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and conſtant affection and reſolution to the Parliament. Their actions ſhew as much as their words, which is further manifeſted in an overthrow given to the Fleet of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to aid the Bebels in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 15 of this moneth nine ſhips ſet out from <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> ſailing with all ſpeed to the coaſts of <hi>Ireland:</hi> but the Lord of the ſeas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpleaſed with their intentions proſpered not their proceedings, but raiſed a great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt which drove them back upon the coaſt of <hi>England<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but fearing to come too neer by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Earle of <hi>Warwicks</hi> Fleet they caſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor about 41. leagues diſtant from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> coaſt, and ſtaying there two dayes by reaſon of a contrary wind, they eſpied two Flemiſh ſhips ſailing neer them, which cauſed a great feare and jealouſie in them, ſuſpecting they would deſcry them to the Dutch Fleet which lay by the way as they were to ſaile homeward, which indeed they did, deſcribing the number of the Spaniſh Fleet, and in what place they lay: which occaſioned the Dutch Admirall (a terrible e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy againſt the Spaniard) with all ſpeed to prepare five ſhips of warre to hoiſe ſail toward the Fleet of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> going himſelfe in perſon, and coming in ſight of them hanged out his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30174:5"/>and making all ready for the fight, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neer made ſhot againſt them, the fight laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full two houres, and many men being ſlain on both ſides, at laſt two of the Spaniſh ſhips were ſunk, which diſhearthed the reſt, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them to flight: the Durch Admirall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them within ſix leagues of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where he took two of them loaden with ammunition, intended for the aid of the Iriſh Rebels, but the other five, being ſwift of ſaile, eſcaped into <hi>Dunkirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords and Commons in Parliament declare. That all ſuch perſons as ſhall upon any pretence whatſoever, aſsiſt His Maieſty in this Warte, with Horſe, Arms, Plate or Money, are Traytors to His Maieſty, the Parliament and Kingdome, and ſhall be brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment for ſo high an offence.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Ordered to be forthwith publiſhed &amp; printed,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30174:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
